Hello, welcome everyone to the active
inference institute uh weekly textbook
reading group. This is the latter
session on Thursdays. Uh we are working
with cohort 8 and we're looking at
chapter 4 of the textbook. So as we know
from chapter one our introduction,
chapter two sort of the low road to
active inference starting with uh basis
theorem uh and kind of basian statistics
or mechanics and then chapter three the
high road to active inference uh drawing
out from the imperative to minimize free
energy in the free energy principle. Now
we reach chapter four which is frankly a
very kind of full chapter that attempts
to in some ways tie together uh these
two different like kind of strong like
uh threads that we saw to active
inference in chapters 2 and chapter 3
while simultaneously finally kind of
introducing us to some core models that
we see often in active inference. uh
other aspects including various
equations. We get to look at uh sort of
graphical representations of models and
so on. So I'll just try and give a
quicker summary of this chapter. Um so
with the intro we're introduced to the
relationship between free energy and
basian inference the form of typical
active inference generative models and
dynamics obtained from minimizing these
models free energy. Specifically, we
look at both discrete and continuous
time models as well as the
neurobiologically motivated idea of
inferential variational message passing
underlying the computations and uh the
the general notion of predictive coding.
So in chap uh section 4.2 two from
basian inference to free energy. Uh
recall that we are here working with
approximate inference rather than exact
basian optimality given the problem of
intractability as well as
neurobiological grounding of limited
resources. So one can you know liken
this to the notion of you know meta
metabolism or you kind of like
conservation of of of resources or
minimizing expenditure in some ways in
the sense of you know our brain is not
fully connected. Uh it it is not a fully
connected neural network. Uh and so
there are various sparse connectivities
going on functional connectivities and
and different kinds of processes
involved. And then from there just the
general notion of us being able to take
in every single bit of you know
observation that comes into you know our
visual space down to uh the idea of of
of computing every single possible
policy in a potentially infinite number
of of worlds like you can start to
imagine like you know that's not quite
how this works. So that the variational
methods are both
mathematically useful as well as kind of
a little bit more grounded in the the
notion of like bounded rationality or
bounded inference. We only have so many
resources available to do the inference
itself let alone maintain our
homeostasis of which that would kind of
be a piece. Um so from there we we're
told that the the mathematics involved
are drawn from uh general fields of
linear algebra uh differentiation and
and integration and calculus and the
tailaylor series expansion in the case
of continuous time models. And so the
the textbook's appendices give further
details on the relationships between
these fields and computations. But
chapter 4 here gives us kind of a
broadstroke view of the maths involved.
Um we know from equation 4.1 you know
this is kind of the familiar basis
theorem we've already been introduced
to. Uh in this case we can kind of see
how we could attempt to derive uh the
probability of in this case the
observations we receive u based upon
sort of these this summation like
summing all possible values of x and
marginalizing
uh such that we can start to kind of
reach that value or or the other way
around. Um and uh nonetheless we're
immediately hit with this issue of
intractability. And so that's where
Jensen's inequality comes in. Um, this
is, you know, in some ways can appear as
sort of a clever trick, but at the same
time, uh, if it's not quite a trick, if
it's, uh, uh, not deceptive. And so what
I mean by that is this is kind of what
allows us to to formalize free energy as
an a kind of lower uh, or excuse me, an
upper bound on basian surprise. So in
this case what we do is that instead of
trying to directly compute um sort of
model evidence we instead use this sort
of variational posterior uh the the
idiom is mind your P's and Q's uh in the
sense that the Q is sort of this this
variational posterior. Now this of
course this term right here would
resolve to one. It's more about what
we're doing with it and how we're sort
of operationalizing it in order to
compute free energy or in this case
negative free energy. Um, right? And so
that's where this term is, right? That's
that's what makes it an upper bound. The
general notion is the log of an average
is always greater than or equal to the
average of a log. And it's because of
that inequality that we're able to to to
kind of formalize this in this way. So
um see so we know that from see
sorry there's just a lot of
interconnectivity between the the
equations in this in this textbook. So
it's like equation 4.3 returning to
basis theorem from before we're now
rewriting it and taking its log. We can
swap in free energy here. Yeah we
already saw is a kind of tractable
quantity. Um and then we can we're shown
the idea of colac uh colac uh leler
divergence which is kind of this core
quantity that we're trying to minimize.
It's kind of like if we can really
minimize this divergence of our
variational posterior from whatever our
model says the the posterior kind of
should be or however this was initially
parameterized. then we can start to
compute free energy. Well, not just
compute it, but like if we can reduce
this divergence, then we're effectively
going to be also reducing variational
free
energy. So,
um KL divergence. So, moving on from
there, we're looking at various kinds of
generative models. And in this case, I
mean, so far we're not even necessarily
in a kind of reinforcement learning
paradigm. There's no sort of uh
necessarily I mean you you could kind of
swap some things around but ultimately
like the this can be as simple you know
they give us the example of like uh you
know um a kind of a binary
classification example for example um of
of trying to kind of predict the the
outcome does someone have you know a
particular uh disease or illness based
upon you know a test. So we can think of
COVID, you know, and this was a one of
the biggest drivers of uh sort of any
kind of financial aspects of of creating
tests and then and then for better or
worse selling them on the on the market
uh so that people could stay safe, but
like how do you how do you devise um a a
very solid like diagnostic COVID test?
Well, you need to look at potential uh
not just true positives and true
negatives, meaning it's truly positive
or truly negative whenever it says
either of those in the test result, but
also the other cases of a false positive
or a false negative, right? So we can
kind of in this case we might have like
some kind of you know prior and then we
we we take in an observation we end up
computing you know we we can basically
try and optimize these kinds of
functions and and then in in terms of an
actually existing COVID test. Um
similarly we we would want to you know
have it be essentially optimized in that
sense like minimize all f false
positives and negatives uh improve all
the true positives and negatives and
then if we start to think I I I kind of
glossed over a lot of that but the the
point is to to reach up to kind of the
more uh exemplar active inference models
and skip ahead just a little bit. So
here we're looking at what in active
inference we're always looking at priors
right we're in a basium sort of
framework and design. So whenever we see
these components of like P parenthesis
pi P uh parenthesis observations given
states P the next state to plus one
given or conditioned on the current
state and the action taken. These all
become kind of components of a model
that are all kind of priors or you could
also view them as models. There's an
interesting question for anyone uh
interested in kind of the
um excuse me
the equations and already at the
beginning of this meeting there was a
mention of like there was a kind of a
discrepancy in the textbook textbook is
uh unfortunately it's not perfect. I
would say it's like as far as I can tell
it's roughly 99% accurate, but there's a
typo here and there. I believe there's a
re-release of the textbook as well that
addresses some of these things, but for
anyone looking at the original one,
unfortunately, there may be a a typo or
two. And that's why we have things like
the KOD and elsewhere to to see if we
can uh answer some of these questions.
And so um you know some people were were
curious like what I just wanted to find
this was interesting because of the the
phrasing. Um what is pi? Page 69 the
authors write at each time step the
current state is conditionally dependent
on the state at the previous time and on
the policy pi currently being pursued.
On page 71 they write thus we can
interpret the priors equations 4.6 six
combined with the likelihood of equation
4.5 is expressing a model pi of a
behavioral sequence. So that's another
tough aspect. Chapter 4 is a good
chapter to really kind of get into in
terms because now the the context here
is that we're combining chapters two and
three, right? We're trying to like we're
kind of restabilizing after these two
different paths that we took to to
understand active inference. Now we're
landing at kind of this central core of
like well now we're talking about models
and now we're talking about fuller
action perception loops and and markoff
blankets and so on. So in this case I
mean as expressing a model this can be
confusing. It's like well we had a
generative model and then what is pi?
Why why is pi this what appears to be an
individual component in some way of one
of these models? Why is that being
called a model? Right? Is or or is it
models all the way down? are these just
model you know nested models and nested
models and in some sense I mean if we
can view you know these these components
are so similar it's like you could
almost extract these out of that larger
model we were just looking at it it it
is a bit of a perspective sort of thing
because let's say prior over pi which we
know from the terminology introduced to
us in the textbook and I can also just
tell you that pi typically represents pi
policies. Policies being sequences of
actions. Uh and so you could have
multiple policies. One policy I have is
to continue leading the the textbook and
and going along with my notes here uh
step by step. Another policy is to for
whatever reason um you know take a break
which which I won't be doing. But there
are many policies I could do and all of
them could have their own respective
kind of trajectories uh beyond just the
immediate next action but actually a
whole sequence of actions that play
together. Is this a model or is this you
know a component of a model? It's it's
kind of both because if you only looked
at this alone, you you know, it could
end up looking like a vector uh of
different prob probabilities over
different um actions or or it could be
uh you know a matrix that has to do with
the probabilities of a bunch of actions
within different policies that then add
up. So it is a model like this isn't a
model of behavior. This is a probability
of different policies. But once you kind
of operationalize this in a broader
context, it itself becomes part of a
larger model. And so whenever we're
putting together active inference
models, we're thinking about things like
like what what is your model? What what
are its components? So I I'm focusing on
this one a lot. This is a this we'll get
to it again in chapter seven, but this
is essentially a POMDP partially
observable marov decision-making
process. This three here uh
this is your state transitions model,
right? So it it is a model in in and of
itself. It's a probability of your next
hidden state given your current hidden
state and policy. So it's like I do
something I think something is going on
at the next step. My three model here
says that you know this will be the next
hidden state the next thing that I
believe this is how I think things
transition in the world in relation to
what's currently going on as well as my
chosen action. It it it's describing
what will come next. Right? So, so
that's where the three comes in. You see
it? So, we feed in the previous step uh
state policy, we reach the next one. And
then with two, this is where we have our
observation model. And so, we have
observations conditioned on states. What
is the probability of my me noticing my
stomach growling if I feel pretty
certain that I am hungry? that I infer
I'm hungry. What what is the probability
if I think I'm hungry? What's the
probability my stomach's going to growl?
You know, um and so we put all these
together and then we essentially run
free energy minimization with this model
and then it'll run free energy
minimization to do two things. It'll um
it'll infer states. So these are all
being inferred. These aren't given to
us. You know, there's maybe some true
states in the environment, you know. So
that maybe maybe this is trying to
model, you know, I don't know if I'm
hungry or not. I only have my bodily
signals to let me know if I might be.
Hunger is essentially a, you know, a
very at the end of the day, it's a very
kind of human linguistic concept based
in real observations and and and
occurrences in the world that we, you
know, come into contact with. So
whenever we minimize free energy, the
notion here is that you know if this was
a model of a person trying to always
figure out if they're hungry or not
based upon their bodily signals and then
they decide once they are hungry oh they
have a belief that if they're hungry
they eat food then it will sate their
hunger and so that you know this be
satiation or being sated at the next
time step it'll move that way and you
can imagine infinitely more complex
scenarios than that where we have many
many different kinds of observations
being fed in all at once you know and I
was just giving a more discreet example
of like it's like a binary hungry not
hungry so from there we're also looking
at um continuous time models and this is
different right this would be this would
be um you know you could measure
someone's heart rate or or some other
kind of continuous value over a whole
slew of values or in some kind of
continuous range um or or from negative
infinity to positive infinity or
otherwise and you do have various
similar dynamics. The textbook uses
different kind of nomenclature really
just to remind you that this is the
continuous case. So before we saw O's
it's in the discrete state space
scenario the POMDP or otherwise um O's
are always for that Y's are always in
the continuous space. So it's like you
have your your O's versus your Y's, you
have your S's versus your X's. And then
we have V as you know and V is a kind of
in a continuous state space. You can
almost think of it as like a certain
kind of level of like a force or
something along those lines. like it
could be a value that's taken you know
we might have some prior to say like it
is coming from a normal distribution or
some other kind of uh distribution
related to a continuous state space uh
it's kind of just you know whenever you
set up a model what do you think is the
best kind of submodel almost that that
that can act as priors in a basian
scheme I have make a best guess that my
force is Gaussian right and and you know
it's going to be centered around zero on
average and you know plus or minus one
for the variance and you would do
similar things for setting up the other
priors. So anytime we do we create an
active inference model we're always just
kind of looking at these many subm
models or components that themselves are
prior and we set them up kind of as
conjugate priors. meaning
it for all intents and purposes for the
sake of right now because I know I'm
kind of going on for some time um you
would want your your priors to be
conjugate in the sense that conjugate is
has a formal definition but to put it
simply it's kind of like saying like it
needs to be a good guess that makes
sense and and so computationally it
needs to sort of make sense. It's like
if if my stomach is growling yes or no
in this discrete space I'm not going to
use you know a Gaussian for that the the
value of.7 doesn't really align with me
trying to say is my stomach growling or
not or am I hungry or not uh maybe a
Bernoli distribution for example would
be a better case which is kind of like a
distribution that describes a you know a
p value a probability value and then for
a for a binary. And so, you know, the
probability of one of those options is P
and the other one is one minus P,
therefore Q. So, we we know that there
we're working in more of a probabilistic
space between two potential values. Uh,
and then um we we we can kind of
approach it that way. So, so Berni might
make more sense. Um, not so much normal
and maybe other way around for this or
not or not. So those are the kinds of
things we think about. Uh we already
went through the POMDP with the
nomenclature. It's you know it's it's we
only see this nomenclature here and then
it doesn't come back again until around
chapter 7. But for anyone who may be
interested um we saw here I mentioned
earlier this was the likelihood model of
observations given states. This can also
be rewritten and this is supposed to be
a shorthand. So it's supposed to be a
useful
uh kind of way of rewriting things.
First cat, this is a categorical
distribution or probability distribution
in this case. Um it's over categories in
a discrete state space, right? What what
is the probability of my stomach is
growling given I'm hungry? What is the
probability that it's not growling given
that I'm hungry? What is the probability
that it's growling given I'm not hungry?
And so we can go through the, you know,
the four different possibilities there.
And then those are kind of like four
different categories. We we could assign
a probability value to all four of those
potential outcomes in this probability
this likelihood model. And then it's
frequently rewritten as the A matrix to
just kind of simplify things. So you
see, you know, if you wanted to talk
about particular indices or particular
things like uh I could be um
uh stomach growling and J could be
stomach not growling. So that's that's
just kind of a note on the termin the
the the sort of syntax here. We'll see
similar things elsewhere. This is
probability of a sequence of states
condition on a policy and that is our B
matrix our state transitions. This more
clearly shows it but I think that
they're trying to show like the kind of
the mathematics behind it. It's a
product and then other important
components. D is one of the simplest.
It's just kind of when you come to a
situation where your priors over states.
We're not even worried about
observations. So O is not in here. We're
not worried about policies. So pi is not
in there. It's simply S. And they use
the one to denote. It's kind of like
this is your starting point because we
always start somewhere. Uh there are
debates in active inference about these
kinds of things but but you know as a
kind of neural process theory active
inference doesn't necessarily give you
you know here's the true magical
starting point right we always come into
a situation and free energy minimization
plays out that's the general sense so if
you're not sure what your starting point
is you're going to have to pick some
prior in some way and and so that's in a
sense what this is could be an outcome
of learning it over time. It could be
quite similar to your last posterior
inference, your last QS,
um you know that then updated what your
priors are now, but essentially it's
just that um we would also see other
important aspects. We haven't seen C
yet. But just as D was the prior over uh
states, we have C which is the prior
over
observations. And so that which also get
relabeled as preferences. It's kind of
like what you want uh so to speak. So I
I I don't want my stomach uh to be
growling. I do want it to not be
growling. Um the reasons for that could
be simply that that's kind of how my C
matrix is constructed in some ways. This
is this gets related to the notion of
homeostasis. Uh in other ways you could
view it as kind of like a set of
attracting points because it's it's kind
of like as we know from from other
chapters if if we don't really have
preferences if you don't have
homeostatic step points that that you're
attracted towards or if due to some kind
of like suboptimal behavior behavior
that's optimal to your given model but
nonetheless behavior that is kind of
suboptimal to the world around you and
your relationship to it. you ultimately
kind of succumb to entropic forces. I'm
the one who cares about my hunger. Um
the the trees outside don't so much care
about that, right? And the the oxygen
around me doesn't so much care about
that. Uh it's just me. So, so I'm just
kind of, you know, the whenever I'm
trying to figure out my policies, my
beliefs of what I should do, uh, a
crucial component is going to be the C
being in there so that I can judge,
well, based on everything I'm seeing,
how close is it to, you know, my
preferences that relate to my
homeostasis? is uh what's going on
actually aligning with what I want to be
occurring or uh what I hope to be
occurring or this doesn't necessarily
have to be described at all as a
rational kind of conscious process in
the sense of you know I have many auto
autonomic processes occurring in my body
that are doing things like uh kind of
maintaining my blood uh oxygen flow and
and regulation and and you know I'm not
really particularly thinking about
breathing right now and yet I'm doing it
because I have various other processes
in me. So, one way we could view that is
these different sort of nested marov
blankets, these different uh organ uh
organs or or however you want to kind of
slice it up. Poor use of words, but uh
they're all minimizing free energy. That
that would be the sort of framework here
from active inference. They're all kind
of doing their own thing. And then you
know that from there we might say like
maybe we hope that there's some kind of
synchrony involved that that allows for
uh almost as if we were looking at it
like a multi- aent uh collaboration
setting or something like that. Like we
would hope that they're properly working
together to where they can all kind of
maintain their own respective uh
homeostats and and and well-being so to
speak, but also contributing to the
broader system that makes up me as the
the whole person or the whole whole
body. Um who who is very, you know,
dynamic in the world and always ever
changing.
Um so I
think beyond that and we got to see G
expected free energy was the the free
energy of the future um which we were
just looking at preferences are there
pragmatic value crucial term information
gain also crucial term two things to
notice are first uh quite eerily similar
to variational free energy
But instead of running this over states
to do state inference, oh my stomach is
growling, I infer that my the the hidden
state of my my body is that I'm hungry.
Um instead, we're scoring for every
available policy. It's expected free
energy. Why is it expected? Because
policies play out over time. And so long
as we have some kind of state
transitions model that adds this
temporal
dimension running left to right that
says, "Oh, this is how I think things
play out over time." And they even have
a relationship to not just what the
previous state was, but also what I do
the policy. We see how that sorry, we
see how that gets kind of insert that's
inserted up here. So G is kind of trying
to figure out which of these should
happen based on my current inferences.
It's how how is that going to happen?
Well, we know that we want to minimize
variational free energy from looking at
the equations in chapter 3. Now we're at
expected free energy and there aren't I
mean you can look at certainly look at
literature on free energy. There are
other potential ways of computing it and
different kinds of message passing
schemes. But for the intents and
purposes of this textbook which also gen
this is the general paradigm is that
there are two different kind of forms of
free energy. Uh one for the moment
moment by moment as it were variational
free energy already saw in chapter 3.
This is expected. Expected is going to
be for policy inference rather than
state inference. How do you def
determine what to do? Another
interesting thing is that both of these
values are negative. This value is
positive. We want to reduce this. So we
actually want these values, we want
information gain to go up. We're used to
looking at uh variational free energy
where you know complexity we want to
reduce complexity and then accuracy we
want to increase accuracy but it has a
minus sign in front of it which is great
because that means by flipping it around
it's like we're reducing variational
free energy we're reducing f by
increasing accuracy meanwhile the
complexity term is positive so we want
to bring that uh down but here both of
these are both of these are negative So,
we actually want to bring up information
gain. What is information gain? Uh-oh.
This is uh Kobach Lebler divergence
looks somewhat similar to the idea of
reducing divergence. But here we're
saying that we actually want to bring it
up. Why would we want to increase
divergence?
This is the kind of exploration term
that quote unquote naturally uh occurs
or or balances uh uh exploration and
exploitation in agent behavior in active
inference agents. This is a crucial
piece that kind of sets apart uh the
behavior that we see in many other kind
of standard reinforcement learning
paradigms and models where oftentimes
instead you're doing things like setting
up some epsilon greedy term uh or or
otherwise basically a value that says
you know maybe 0.9% of point probability
0.9 you do what you think the best thing
should be the best policy that should be
0.1 prob probability that you just do
something random. And the concern there
for reinforcement learning paradigms is
oh well we can't just have a model who
always jumps to what it thinks is the
best thing. What happens if it you know
arrives in some local minimum and then
just stays there. It will never know how
to get out of that suboptimal situation.
It's optimal to the model. It thinks
it's great. The model keeps going with
what it thinks is best to do. But in the
actual broader scheme in the environment
that it's in uh you know it's it's
actually not performing well or it's uh
performing in a kind of suboptimal way
right um so here this actually plays out
naturally so to speak by saying oh what
should I
do well I want to figure out what's
going on conditioned on what I saw and
what I
did versus what's going on versus what I
did. So, this is kind of like saying,
"Oh, I want to choose to do things that
are actually very different from what I
thought would was would be going on
because I received these real
observations from around me." It's kind
of like saying I will choose to do thing
go out of my way to do things to try and
actually change my own beliefs about the
the impact of my actions on the world
around me. So imagine someone choosing
to open up a textbook. It it is
not getting you straight A's right now
from just reading it. It's not it's it's
not really accomplishing a lot in terms
of keeping your homeostasis going, but
in some ways it is certainly teaching
you things and so that is information
gained. So it's sort of a a simplistic
way of looking at it but it's simply the
sense of we you know in this sense this
is a way of kind of quantifying
mathematizing formalizing the sense of
exploratory behavior. And just as with
any other equation, this equation holds.
So it's not this is not going to this
equation itself is not going to change.
So you don't have to manually define
anything and you don't have to be
creative by saying oh with 0.1
probability you just do something random
and that's how I help you to not get
stuck in a hole. Uh right and it can be
broken up into to other terms too just
as we saw with with variational free
energy. So like expected ambiguity it's
like what is the expectation or this
posterior uh what is the expected
entropy of a sequence of observations
given a sequence of hidden state
inferences. So it's it's kind of these
kinds of terms like ambiguity it's kind
of like it starts relating to the idea
of one to many or many to many mappings.
It's like, do if if if I'm going to go
into a um a restaurant, do I expect to
see that they're selling food or if I go
into this building, do I expect it might
be selling food or it might be selling
tires or might be selling this or this?
It's like I don't know if I want to go
if I'm really hungry, I don't know if
that would be the first building I would
go into. I think I would go into the one
where it seems very clear that they're
selling like the food and then even
better than that food that
I want. Uh right, is another simple
example. So um I think that we've
touched on various things now you we've
already touched on the categorical
distributions
uh we've touched on there's entropy term
um we've touched on you know the the the
significance of linear algebra
um we have the softmax function which is
frequently used softmax is quite it's
often used in active inference to kind
of um you we we we have to normalize our
distribution so that they sum to one
espe you know in the discrete state
space setting. So if probability of you
know being hungry is 0.5 then
necessarily the the probability of not
being hungry is also 0.5 you know 1
minus.5 is.5. Um here softax kind of uh
normalized exponentials. So what we're
doing is that we're kind of
exponentiating
uh these these differences. We're not
just normalizing a distribution, but
we're actually amplifying the values
that are the strongest or or reducing
the values that are the weakest or if
there's already uh you know a lot of
similarity between the values, it might
actually flatten them. It's kind of like
saying oh if you're if you're if if
you're generally uncertain then it's
kind of amplifying it to where you're
you're very uncertain like almost like a
uniform distribution and the other way
around. So this this plays out in
different ways. It plays out in expected
uh not expected free energy. It plays
out in policy inference as a way of sort
of renormalizing everything. It's like
okay you you have your your priors over
your policies the E matrix. Uh you you
have your um expected free energy over
each policy. So into the future kind of
related to deliberate planning and then
you have variational free energy over
each policy if you're including that in
your equation. So then that's kind of
moment by moment. So in policy inference
it's like you have these uh these three
different terms. Uh I don't I don't
believe that particular yeah the
particular equation is not oh okay this
is it they've left out E. you don't
necessarily have to include E in the
sense of creating incilico you know kind
of um experiments or or or uh
simulations active inference uh kind of
action perception loops but but more
often than not you would include e here
as well and it's kind of like saying
what you do is in a sense a kind of uh
normalized
exponentiated function of the policies
uh that you scored based on expected
free energy minim minimization. G uh the
way you scored them based on variational
free energy uh you know complexity minus
accuracy. Um and then E would be your
habits, your priors over policies. They
write it in this way I believe to just
kind of like make a point. This is like
an introductory sort of point over um
sort of how F and G both can play into
what you choose to do. But I've always
been fascinated by the fuller write out
of this uh equation from sort of like a
behavioral or social science perspective
because what it's saying is that if you
did have the e here, it's like saying
what you do is in some way a kind of
balanced
uh uh comp uh a kind of balanced um
outcome of what you deliberately plan to
do versus f. So just maintaining
yourself in the moment. Uh keeping
things like as simple as possible and no
simpler while still being accurate. Uh
and then also your habits. So what what
what you've done in the past, what's
going on in the moment, and also what
you plan to do for the future, right?
Which goes a little bit further than uh
sort of the the conaman thinking fast
and slow scheme. I I saw I was uh
whenever I ran a workshop last year,
there was a professor who was asking
about the relationship there. And I'm
like, well actually we have we have
three different component. We we kind of
have the past and the present and the
future all kind of here in their own
respective ways instead of just the the
the diatic relationship between a fast
and slow system. We start getting into
variational message passing. So we'll in
belief propagation these things come up
much more strongly next chapter which is
why I didn't u put too much emphasis on
those for right now.
But we get a little bit of a a little
bit of um a preview suppose the the
notion would be that we're just passing.
So we have different prediction errors
and uh hidden state inferences
uh at different time
steps one to another over the course of
different observations that are received
sequentially. states that are inferred
over
time. And
that's general sense. We're shown
generalized coordinates of motion. Those
will come up much more in chapter 8 on
continuous time models. It's like, well,
how do we figure out state transitions
if we're not just going from hungry to
not hungry to hungry to not hungry?
Instead, it's a whole range of values
potentially. And it's we're essentially
we're just looking at derivatives which
those who've done you know differential
equations and calculus and in in other
settings uh including you know working
with neuroiming data or otherwise this
will probably not come off as
particularly foreign uh to them. But the
the notion would be that we'd add some
number of Taylor series expansion kind
of terms. uh more often than not they
claim that around six are sufficient all
depending on the way that you're fitting
your model and what seems to hold. So
I'll kind of
stop there. We do we do see some more
relationships between you know other
fields other other ways of doing things.
we have uh maximum a posterior uh
estimates for for states and and
relating it to that
um lelass
approximations
and yeah so it it goes on for some time
but it's it's it's just there's so much
of this chapter that they try to fit in
all at once while knowing that the next
chapter is going to get into message
passing the chapter after that is going
to get into the bare bones of modeling
chapter Chapter seven is going to get
into the POMDP model. Chapter eight's
going to get into these continuous time
models. Chapter nine will get into kind
of the fun uh aspects of of of data
analysis and what you can actually do
from with the results of these models.
So, I'm going to I'm going to leave it
there. Apologies for anyone if if they
um had anything uh they really wanted to
get into that I might have spoken over.
But I'll I'll go ahead and open up the
floor if anyone has any uh talking
points or anything interesting that
stuck out to them whenever they're
reading this textbook and maybe we can
have a look at it. Thanks.
So the the joint probability
distribution is the thing generated by
the generative model, right?
Yeah. So the joint
distribution between states and
observations, we might be able to pull
up a representation of that, but
essentially like a the probability of X
comma Y or the probability of S comma O
um is essentially your generative model,
right? It's a it's a model over states
and observations together. And it's the
way that we sort of optimize it and
figure out, you know, the posterior
states if you're trying to infer states,
which is sort of the the active
inference way, but also the basian way
in general, is to kind of break apart
that joint distribution and apply
different forms of marginalization and
variational inference in order to
actually use it to to compute
posteriors. it to make sure I really
answer your question though just yes the
the generative model the agent the
organism in question is is essentially a
joint distribution over over states and
observations it is of course a little
more complex because in the the textbook
you know the the way that they show
basis theorem is that we're repeatedly
relating states and
observations but really once we bring in
the capacity for planning and decision
making and taking actions where suddenly
it's like well pi where was that in
basis theorem it's like well it's still
a basian framework it's still we still
have a prior for it and whenever it
comes to policy inference we still infer
policies but we're using expected free
energy to as as kind of the primary
means of doing that um all this is to
say you could write a generative model
very differently uh that had more
components. So it could be a joint
distribution of um I liked this if I
could find it. And for anyone interested
in programming
um yeah anyone who who's interested in
Python programming or otherwise or wants
to take a crack at discrete state spaces
um this has been uh for two to three
years um a uh kind of the the primary
library if there were a primary library
for uh doing active inference in Python
but only for discrete state spaces. So
unfortunately you're not going to be
able to get into your your Gaussian
distributions necessarily but um here
they write a generative model I've sort
of liked this nomenclature
um with a a slight discrepancy that I
want to mention. So this writing of it
you we're we're familiar with the fact
that this is a prob a probability
distribution. It's wrapped with a
capital P. We have O for observations, S
for states. As before, we have U, which
that's, you know, uh that's something to
watch out for in active inference
literature. Sometimes people decide to
use sort of their own uh terms. Th this
one kind of makes sense because
sometimes the textbook will use the
letter U to denote an individual action.
So a se a sequence of use or a sequence
of actions then denotes a particular
policy with a policy being a sequence of
actions. So this this from the
textbook's perspective this would be
taken as an action but here they're kind
of using it as the more general this is
a policy and then this u this final kind
so this fee is for
hyperparameters what we haven't even
talked about hyperparameters yet in at
this point in the in the textbook but
the idea is you could kind of say oh
here are all the parameters specific to
this model not just its priors or or its
understanding or or the way that it
processes observations and states and
policies, but also what are all these
little specific aspects, you know, uh
it's it's uh again not in chapter 4,
it's in the second half of the book, I
think, but the we I believe we've
already been introduced at least to the
concept of learning as opposed to
inference. With inference, we've already
talked about it a lot. We're inferring
states from minimizing variational free
energy f. We've talked about minimizing
um expected free energy to figure out
what to do in policy inference. Uh
learning however would be what happens
whenever one of your priors or some kind
of parameter on it itself changes. So
that could be precision values for
example. Precision values what are
those? They are neurobiologically
generally an attempt at trying to model
sort of neurotransmitters and
transmission or synaptic gain uh in
different ways um based on you know some
of the empirical work that Fristen
Schwenbeck and others have done. Uh one
way that you can view expected free
energy as a form of deliberate planning
is that whenever it's uh kind of
modulated by this uh they use the term
gamma but it is a a precision value. And
so if it goes up it's kind of relatable
to sort of dopamine uh in the sense that
dopamine tends to kind of with with a
depletion or or diminishment or or or or
insufficient
dopamine so to speak or maybe the the
re-uptake process is not quite strong
enough. What happens is that you end up
with a person who's very lethargic,
right? And so there's not a lot of
confidence. They might have ideas of
what they should do, but they won't
necessarily feel confident in their
capacity to, you know, fulfill them, to
get up and do what it is they need to
do. You know, in in very extreme levels,
it starts to more or less mirror, you
know, the kinds of behaviors we see in
like major depressive disorder from a
psychiatry perspective. Um and and then
on the other hand, a very extreme amount
of dopamine would make someone very very
enthusiastic about the policies that
they kind of, you know, they they would
be almost excessively confident in what
they're going to do. And that can kind
of manifest manifest in v uh various
ways as well including like leading to
different forms of delusions uh or or
even like kind of um kind of psychosis
or or different kinds of hyperprecise
priors that are they're so specific and
and are difficult to sort of unlearn or
modulate appropriately that it leads to
what we could kind of definitively
defined as pathologic behaviors. I don't
mean to scare everyone by giving those
extreme examples. Um but the but the
notion is that precisions precision
values would be something that kind of
modulate the strength or the certainty
or the confidence of each of these kind
of inter nested models your policy or
behavioral model your likelihood model
or your state transitions model or what
other other component you have. Um and
then this itself could change. You could
put a prior on this prior. um in which
case you would in a discrete state space
setting you'd use a matrix derish
distribution which is kind of like a
categorical distribution but it doesn't
have to be normalized. So it you it
could start to kind of collect observ
it's kind of like saying yes this is a
marov environment like a kind of marov
marovian paradigm we're looking at here
going from you know from one step to the
next and the next step here doesn't
necessarily fully depend on what came
before but nonetheless you can kind of
build up observations along the way and
build them up in your hyperparameter
what does that mean in more plain terms
it's kind of like saying we can still
follow this paradigm
And yet long-term memory exists
um and and it matters but the way that
it matters is that it changes how the
model works from time step to time step
or at least as frequently as the the
model is learning. So
um so essentially learning would involve
actually changing the parameters of the
model itself.
So fe as a kind of standard this is a
fuller representation of what a
generative model might look like in in
how we often do active inference. You
have observation states but you also
have
essentially policies or behav the
behavioral component and then you have
all these different hyperparameters you
may or may not have included in
constructing your your model. And so
like with with PIMDP what would you do
there? This itself can be kind of ex
helpful or explanatory. Um but the idea
is that you're going to compose an
agent. It's going the agent can infer
its states can infer states. Infer S or
infer X. Um here we'll say S for the
discrete state space setting. How does
it do it? Well, it takes in a new
observation. So it takes in an
observation right here. And we're going
to call this function infer states.
Infer states is incredibly complex. Um,
and so I've been working with a PhD
student recently and and and he and I
were very excited to work with PMDP, but
then we noticed we might need to make
some modifications and it's like, well,
actually in first states it's quite
complex underneath. So that's been a
little bit of a a journey, but it's been
it's been fun and pretty enlightening.
Um, there's always more to learn. So you
would set up an agent by supplying it
with its A matrix and these other
matrices I mentioned earlier. The A the
likelihood matrix like probability of
observations given states the B matrix
which would be the probability of the
next state given the current state and
the thing I chose to do policy. Uh C. So
you're telling your you're saying what
your agent's preferences are over
observations it receives priors over
observations. And then D prior over
states where where where it's starting
point about what it believes is
currently going on might be uniform
might be completely uncertain or it
might be very certain that something is
already going on and then it'll be yet
to be seen how it responds to receiving
a new observation and then inferring
states.
So um
uh so I had another question.
Uh so you you you have these you have
these probabilities that are part of
your model, but how do you know that the
model isn't just like I don't know an AI
hallucination or something? Like how how
do you know
that the underlying states of your model
are any good? Um,
how do you know if
the like is it kind of like how do you
know if your model is uh so somewhere
else in the book it says there's a
difference between the states of your
model and the states of your actual
world? How do you know they're not like
really different?
That's the tough part. Uh you might not.
And what I mean by that is um in the in
the same sense that you know because and
I apologize I don't mean to sound
strange but I'm just kind of using
metaphors here uh or or analogies. It's
kind of like if you have a you know the
existence of science as a field involves
people going out gathering observations
to infer hidden states what they think
about the world and and they can do it
repeatedly and they they consider that
to be evidence that they're pulling in
for you know their theory. So you can
view that as an agent a scientist here
is an agent. They're collecting
observations to infer hidden states of
the world if they want to understand uh
climate, you know, and they use
different kinds of scientific implements
to gather that as evidence in order to
make an inference about kind of, you
know, would you know, make a forecast
about what's going to happen or what,
you know, or me pulling out my phone to
look at what the temperature is right
now to make a best guess about what the
temperature is outside.
This is not in some ways dramatically
different than that that you know and
this is an agent who takes an
observation and infers states. So, so to
say something in here might be bad, it's
like well
um you would kind of need some you might
need some external observer for example
who who does know kind of a closer a
better approximation to the true state
of the environment and they could tell
you if it's it's bad or not. But um
you're ultimately it doesn't matter if
you're using active inference or if
you're using a deep learning
reinforcement learning u model or agent.
It's like it's the it's kind of the same
thing either way. You just kind of you
set up a model that you think is most
appropriate to the situation based on
previous research which itself is an
observation for you to infer your own
states about what the priors on this
thing should be. And it's kind of like
the you see that that's the kind of
nestedness that we get out of looking at
things from the active inference sort of
framework. Everything we take in is an
observation. and we just infer states.
And so, um, I mean, or you could look at
it in the context of a particular
simulation. So, you could say, oh,
there's there's an agent and we want
them to, you know, uh, oh, we have a we
have a a mouse and a teammates, right?
And it despite the fact that it keeps
going left and it keeps missing the
cheese and it keeps instead get getting
a a negative stimulus like a little
shock, it still keeps going left. Why is
that? For us, the observers, we think,
well, that's definitely suboptimal
behavior that the rat wants the cheese.
Why does it keep going left even though
it's getting contradictory evidence
repeatedly that the cheese is in fact
not on the left? In that case, we might
make a a a kind of more conclusive
statement that this is suboptimal. And
then we could from there say like, oh,
if we view the mouse as a generative
model or at least being equipped with a
generative model that it's using to try
and solve that problem of getting the
cheese or navigating the maze, then in
that case you could say like, oh, that
that's bad. Like there are bad priors in
this model. Like that might be one for
way of describing like how you might
have criteria for that. Um if you want a
model that you're in in a machine
learning paradigm, you often take you
know you take data and you split it into
a training set and a testing set and
then you train the model in the training
data and then you test it by looking at
how well it performs versus the true
values in the testing data, right? And
you can use some kind of metric like
mean root mean squared error or or
otherwise depending on your this the
states basically whatever error metric
is most appropriate for that scenario
and then that would be a kind of
measurement criteria to say how good or
bad your model is right and then from
there it's like well for a particular
problem like you know trying to predict
the
MNIST data set it's like well maybe
there's some models that are almost
perfect at it and others that aren't.
But then maybe there's another problem
that's very very hard to where the best
model that anyone has ever published on
for that particular problem at hand.
They don't the best there a model that
they could do was a model that's about
50% accurate which would be a coin flip
which would not be useful um in a sense
but uh but it's it just kind of can go
on and on. So it's it's more about
getting used to the the idea of thinking
about modeling what it is we're trying
to do whenever how often can you find
would you say uh a model like this
for that is that is significantly not
just better than a coin flip but like
significantly better by by some
criterion
uh to model something complex like like
a cat
how how do you get a model it's like
better than I don't
know how do you make a model that can
that's good enough to predict it for a
while.
Yeah, that's a good I mean it's a good
question and it's honestly it's a very
broad I mean anyone who does modeling it
it's there are many different kinds of
answers to that question. Um ultimately
we all kind of want to achieve that
which is why I keep speaking so openly
instead of pointing at formulas. Um I
mean if one way to do it from the active
inference perspective it's like well you
can just you know figure out what you
think the cat if you're trying to model
a cat or a cat's behavior right then
what you could do is you could say well
here are some things I think the cat
would do or policies available to the
cat maybe it runs maybe it scratches
maybe it you know such and such or you
could look at a continuous state space
setting where it's like oh it has multip
multiple things it does each with their
respective kind of continuous values
like how hard does it scratch or how
fast does it run when it runs. Um which
can vary, right? And that's kind of the
utility of using the continuous state
space. Um, but you just kind of go with
your best guesses of how you think that
would work first. And then second, you
would, you know, in in reality, if
you're trying to model some kind of
realw world phenomena, then you would
want to find some kind of data from the
cat that you can actually record and and
use sort of as your data that you will
use to fit your model to it. Right? The
notion here in active inference is that
we're not trying to model an entire
brain or the entirety of an organism.
That would kind of start to defeat the
purpose of some of the variational
methods going on here and some of the
the the the I mean you could
theoretically, but but the idea would be
that we're trying to model the the
the we're trying to model the model that
the agent uses to solve a problem.
either maybe it's a cat in an open world
where there isn't really a very specific
problem. But if you view it as well the
cat also has to breathe oxygen and it
also has to eat food and it also has to
sleep you know other things that it
needs to do in order to stay alive to
maintain its homeostasis. Then you
already start you start to have the
trappings of a C matrix like that that
those would be the homeostats the
preferences and and then you can think
of what it would do to accomplish and
then from there if you fit the model to
real data from
Oh yeah sure sure
I'll go ahead and stop John we can
continue this conversation some other
time I appreciate your questions um
thanks
everyone more questions on Discord
Thanks all. See you. Thank you, Andrew.
Bye.